Hey friends, we're glad you're still with us here at Microsoft Virtual Academy as we do our intro to ASP.NET Core.
We're learning all about razor pages and our application.
This module will be a little longer.
Yes it will.
And it will probably have us making some mistakes together,and that's okay.
And we're gonna try not to hide anything from you.
We are following the documentation as we hope that are, and maybe you can follow along.
Pause, try stuff out, and maybe Google with Bing.
Google with Bing.
If you have trouble and get stuck.
Yeah, and we will have links to the documentation right underneath this recording.
All right, so we're gonna try to make a CRUD page.
What is CRUD?
Create,read, update, delete.
All right, so a CRUD application maps verbs from CRUD to verbs that we're used to using,like get is a get, so it would be like a read.
And if you're gonna create something, it would be a post.
So you'd fill out a form, you'd hit submit, and it would post the data, that's a create Then you can maybe read it back and look at in edit page or then maybe delete it.
So if we succeed, we'll have the simple form,maybe create some customers, put them in a fake database And we'll be okay
Yeah, and I will be learning more about databases in the intermediate course as well
Yes,well like a whole section on databases.
So for now, we're gonna be doing it in an in-memory database.
Okay, so let's do the best we can.
We're gonna use the same web application one that we created before.
We saw in the previous modules where we added MVC, but of course all of that stuff was added for us because we went File > New Project,and we picked Web Application, all right?
So here in configure services, we've got AddMvc.
But we're gonna make our little in-memory database here.
We're gonna say services.AddDbContext<>
Yeah, and give it name
And we gonna create a thing called AppDbContext.
We can name it whatever we want to.
We haven't written this yet, but we will.
I'm gonna hit Ctrl+dot.
And it's saying, hey, do you need an AppDbContext?
Do you wanna go and generate one of those?
I wanna go ahead and say yes.
So it's gone and done that, and we'll deal with that in a minute.
And again, I will very likely make mistakes, so you'll bear with me I hope.
I opened up the parentheses there.
And I'm gonna pass in some options.
- And the option I'm gonna pass in for my database context are options -UseInmemory.
-Use -In.
MemoryDatabase.
Yes, but the reason why that's not showing,that perfect.
-We need to add -why is that not showing up?
So we need to add the entity framework.
So we need to use
And I probably should have added that first, and
I would have gotten IntelliSense.
-True -Let's try that.
If we go back up to the top.
So we add the EntityFrameworkCore beforehand.
Look, you see that little arrow there that's pointing down?
That means that this method came in was included by the fact that we just did that UseIn.
That's called an extension method.
It's along for the ride.
And you see it actually says extension.
That wasn't there seconds ago.
No, it wasn't.
Add InMemoryDatabase, some name All right,And then we look at the squiggle and we worry.
Does the squiggle mean something?
So, here it's saying AddDbContext.
Well, we never really went and did anything with that AddDbContext.
Let's go over there and fix that.
I'm gonna right click and say go to definition.
And let's work on our database context.
This is kind of standard stuff, so don't worry about it too much.
But basically this is representing the database.
I'm hitting Ctrl+dot there.
And I'll say make it an AppDbContext,
this is an constructor, all right?
Okay, and we're gonna take in some options.
ContextOptions.
-Oops, optoons -Options.
Options, pass up to the base class those options.
I'm gonna put that.
What I'm trying to zoom and make it helpful for you, I end up making it worse for myself.
Well, at least you have other people in mind.
-I do. And then -You have to set it of some sort.
We have a set of, we're gonna say customers?
So we have a set of customer.
Customer does not exist here.
That's why it's squiggled out.
And then we do a getter, setter, get ; set, okay?