Hey friends, we're glad you're still with us here at Microsoft Virtual Academy as we do our intro to ASP.NET Core.
We're learning all about razor pages and our application.
This module will be a little longer.
Yes it will.
And it will probably have us making some mistakes together,and that's okay.
And we're gonna try not to hide anything from you.
We are following the documentation as we hope that are, and maybe you can follow along.
Pause, try stuff out, and maybe Google with Bing.
Google with Bing.
If you have trouble and get stuck.
Yeah, and we will have links to the documentation right underneath this recording.
All right, so we're gonna try to make a CRUD page.
What is CRUD?
Create,read, update, delete.
All right, so a CRUD application maps verbs from CRUD to verbs that we're used to using,like get is a get, so it would be like a read.
And if you're gonna create something, it would be a post.
So you'd fill out a form, you'd hit submit, and it would post the data, that's a create Then you can maybe read it back and look at in edit page or then maybe delete it.
So if we succeed, we'll have the simple form,maybe create some customers, put them in a fake database And we'll be okay
Yeah, and I will be learning more about databases in the intermediate course as well
Yes,well like a whole section on databases.
So for now, we're gonna be doing it in an in-memory database.
Okay, so let's do the best we can.
We're gonna use the same web application one that we created before.
We saw in the previous modules where we added MVC, but of course all of that stuff was added for us because we went File > New Project,and we picked Web Application, all right?
So here in configure services, we've got AddMvc.
But we're gonna make our little in-memory database here.
We're gonna say services.AddDbContext<>
Yeah, and give it name
And we gonna create a thing called AppDbContext.
We can name it whatever we want to.
We haven't written this yet, but we will.
I'm gonna hit Ctrl+dot.
And it's saying, hey, do you need an AppDbContext?
Do you wanna go and generate one of those?
I wanna go ahead and say yes.
So it's gone and done that, and we'll deal with that in a minute.
And again, I will very likely make mistakes, so you'll bear with me I hope.
I opened up the parentheses there.
And I'm gonna pass in some options.
- And the option I'm gonna pass in for my database context are options -UseInmemory.
-Use -In.
MemoryDatabase.
Yes, but the reason why that's not showing,that perfect.
-We need to add -why is that not showing up?
So we need to add the entity framework.
So we need to use
And I probably should have added that first, and
I would have gotten IntelliSense.
-True -Let's try that.
If we go back up to the top.
So we add the EntityFrameworkCore beforehand.
Look, you see that little arrow there that's pointing down?
That means that this method came in was included by the fact that we just did that UseIn.
That's called an extension method.
It's along for the ride.
And you see it actually says extension.
That wasn't there seconds ago.
No, it wasn't.
Add InMemoryDatabase, some name All right,And then we look at the squiggle and we worry.
Does the squiggle mean something?
So, here it's saying AddDbContext.
Well, we never really went and did anything with that AddDbContext.
Let's go over there and fix that.
I'm gonna right click and say go to definition.
And let's work on our database context.
This is kind of standard stuff, so don't worry about it too much.
But basically this is representing the database.
I'm hitting Ctrl+dot there.
And I'll say make it an AppDbContext,
this is an constructor, all right?
Okay, and we're gonna take in some options.
ContextOptions.
-Oops, optoons -Options.
Options, pass up to the base class those options.
I'm gonna put that.
What I'm trying to zoom and make it helpful for you, I end up making it worse for myself.
Well, at least you have other people in mind.
-I do. And then -You have to set it of some sort.
We have a set of, we're gonna say customers?
So we have a set of customer.
Customer does not exist here.
That's why it's squiggled out.
And then we do a getter, setter, get ; set, okay?
Customer is squiggled out.
The type or namespace 'Customer' could not be found.
Well, that's true cuz we haven't made one yet.
We had not made it up.
l could type control dot, but l am gonna click show potential fixes.
This is kind of interesting.
Here it's saying, well, I can go and make customer for you.
But look at this here.
It's suggesting other packages that have the word customer and the name customer in it.
So these are other NuGet packages,packages up in the world.
Yeah, ain't that cool?
That's very cool.
-Package out there that has the word customer in it -Has the word customer in it
No, I don't want those.
But if I was doing something with JSON or doing something with some technology that I knew I will need the NuGet packages, later it will go get it for me.
So I'm gonna say generate in new file, that seems reasonable.
-It does -All right, this generated that.
Now notice it just appeared.
-There it is -And now I'm gonna right click and say go to definition
It is worth pointing out that I could also right click and say Peak Definition.
-And could you write in there? -I could.
I think that would be a little weird.
But then I can click on this little tab right here Promote to Document, and now I've jumped into that document.
So I can peek and then if I type a little bit,I was like this is tiresome, then I could jump even higher.
-That's pretty smooth. -It is pretty smooth.
-All right, I'll show you another smooth tip. -I know it.
-Yeah? You wanna suggest? -The tab tab thing?
-Yes, ready? -Prop Tab.
-Tab, tab -int Tab Id Enter Enter prop Tab Tab string Enter Tab Name.
-How cool is that? -It's cool, and I always forget to use it.
-You gotta use it. -I always forget to use it and it's awesome.
-There's so much good stuff in there. -There's also propfull.
-What does that do? -That gives you a backing variable.
There's propa,which I don't know what it does but it's crazy.
There's propg for a getter with a private setter.
Yeah, a bunch of stuff.
-Have you done a blog post on all the properties
There's a bunch of snippets,I could go all day.
But I'm just gonna use prop for now.
So this is customer, so customers have an ID,a unique ID.
And they have a name.
And they could probably have an email,they could have all these things.
-Yeah. -We'll start with name for now, but should name have some constraints?
-It should. -We have an idea of data annotation.
There's annotation on that data, yes.
So one of the things is that you probably want someone to enter their name, right?
-We wanna force them. -We wanna force them, so we want to make sure it some sort of required, right?
So required, and I'm putting that as a notation here and I'm gonna hit Ctrl+dot, again.
When you learn that these things exist and you're thinking about them rather than typing in all this stuff for the using,you're just gonna type required.
Hit Ctrl+dot, and then hit Enter.
Line 1 just appeared there And then we'll force the length as well.
We'll be silly for a moment, we'll say a length of 10.
That's not a very good length.
That is not a good length at all.
But that might allow us to do some validation later.
And then we'll change it to a longer length.
All right, so let's back up for a second and see what we did here.
So we have in our start up an InMemoryDatabase.
Not a SQLserver or a.
Whatever just in memory database.
We have a beginnings of a customer, unique ID and a name Some annotations on it, and then a little class here that's kind of empty.
That is our a list of customers and actually what's customer Singular here.
-Yeah. -That should be customers.
-Okay, because, you have a set. -This is a set of customers.
So the one thing, how are we going to see this information?
Well, we're going to need to probably put some in the database and then,once we have them in the database, list them out.
Like how are we going to visually see it?
Yeah, so there's a bit of a chicken and the egg problem there.
Do we make the listing page first and list them out?
But we really can't cuz we don't have any.
-You don't anything, yeah. -Or we make a create page first.
-So it's CRUD. -We'll do the C first, okay?
-So over in -The pages folder.
Pages, let's do create.
Now, we're not going to say new file like we did before.
No, you're going to create a new Razor Page or if you go to New File.
Let me do that again.
Right click and I have two choices I have new.
-And then. -Page or I can say item.
Yeah, New Item.
And they should be the option to pick Razor Page.
Right, so you got a couple different options here and this is all the different things that you could make.
I'm gonna go and right click and say add Razor page, and I wanna point out that I'm not gonna do it for this because it will be a little bit cheating but after we're all done, first, we make you suffer.
-And then we show you the easy way And then we show you the easy way
We could create that model and say Razor page is using entity framework CRUD, and then it will then scaffold or generate.
-Every single -All the hard parts that we're about to do.
But it's more fun to do, no no,it's more fun to do it ourselves, don't you think?
-All right. -All right, lets do it ourselves.
People can fast forward if they don't like it.
The page name would be create.
Uh-huh, and then we're gonna use a layout, we saw that.
And then, here it says Generate PageModel,that's that code behind of that page model.
We could say no and then do that in line, if we wanted to.
All right. So let's see if that works.
Thinking, thinking, thinking.
We're gonna watch in the right hand side here as create should appear.
And sticking well because it's doing quite a bit of scaffolding.
Well, it's scaffolding up some workforce but it's also gonna build the application to see if it still builds.
And if it's running a scarf-folder.
And scar folder is something that you can go on a nd read about and write your own if you feel like it.
So here we gotta create.
So let's see what we have in there.
Let's see it gives us a page.
It gave us a default model, a title, looks like a header, and then some validation scripts, and then presumably we can just start typing our pages or whatever.
Let's look at the backend.
It made a create model that has a get.
So this is the function that happens when we get stuff.
Okay.
All right, so we're gonna need to make form code.
All right, so form that would have actually just one entry?
Yeah, so we'll say enter your name, figure, all right.
And who knows if this will work, again, we're gonna learn.
Now, this is interesting, noticed that when I typed form Why is it in purple?
Turns purple, so that is a tag helper, this is some related elements that are gonna be on the server for processing so the server knows about purple elements, and ill do some processing of them.
Typically when you're in HTML, you have like a P tag or an image tag or div, and that's just strings that get sent off to the client.
But when we're generating this stuff on the server side,there might be an opportunity for ASP.NET Core to improve it,to change it, to add stuff.
So it knows about form.
Form is a magic tag and we can go and type things like this,you see it says asp colon.
Yeah, so is that indication that that is a tag helper or some sort of action?
Right these things aren't html.
No.
Those are tag helpers.
You'll never see asp hyphen something being sent all the way out to the browser.
These are not HTML.
They're hints to the server.
So if when we run this application, and we go into the F12 tools, we will not see- You shouldn't see those.
Okay. Exactly.
So we're gonna say form, this is gonna be basic method= a,yep see- Okay.
Get, post, put, delete.
We'll say post So we're gonna go and post.
Here's the end of our form.
Say div, name, and then we'll need a text box.
Yep so some sort of input tag.
Yep input.
Now, this is interesting.
We could do an input tag the way we usually do or we could say ASP.NET4.
Okay.
And we're gonna say Customer.Name.
See how it's all purple?
That ASP 4 is gonna look at that model, okay?
Now, it's saying here, I don't know what a Customer is.
What's going on with that?
It's never heard of Customer before.
We'll come back and fix that in a second.
Then we'll have an input for submitting that form, okay?
But we have a problem here,where it doesn't know what Customer is.
What is the model for this page?Right, it's the
The Create
CreateModel, so let's go look at that.
Peek into Definition, okay.
I wanna point out how I'm moving around.
I'm right-clicking and saying Go To Definition is also a hotkey for that.
So this is an important reminder, just as a programmer,you don't wanna necessarily find yourself going over and looking around all the files all the time.
You can navigate- To it, right?
To it directly, you can navigate logically, as they say.
-Okay, all right. -Did you?
Cut something out from- Yeah.
-Okay -Great.
-There we go -I cut out CreateModel, thank you.
Right so, our create model is gonna need to know about customers, because that's gonna show up on the page.
So public Customer, that's a type.
-That's a name -You can tell by the color.
It's a little confusing.
But, the property is called Customer, and the type is called Customer.
And, this is going to need that database context,so we are going to make a little Database here.
And this is just being the voice of the person doing this at home.
Why have you made it private read only?
So that's a great point.
I don't want people who get a hold of create model to be poking around and talking directly to the database.
So, it's gonna be private, just for me where me is CreateModel.
And it's read only which means I'm gonna assign it once, and I don't want anyone to touch it after that.
Yeah. Okay.
So I'm making it just for me and making sure I can't mess with it afterwards.
Excellent, excellent question.
So then, we'll make our- CreateModel Our constructor.
And remember how dependency injection works.
We don't make an AppDbContext we ask for one.
We ask for it by putting it in our constructor.
We can have as many of these as we want.
We can have food and bar, etc, etc, etc.
This is the one we want for now.
And then I'm just going to say hey, this one equals this one.
I'm going to squirrel it away and hang onto it, so now I've got one.
So that says there's this database, and I want to know about it.
This says there's a customer.
If I go back over to create, I can hover over that and see it's getting me probably IntelliSense too.
Yep, see. Now, it is.
So, it knows about customer because it's hanging off of the model.
So as we're running the application.
Technically, I should be able to go to this page,hover over customer name and see what names we've put in there?
You should be able to click on that,you should be able to have IntelliSense.
If you did a break point,you should be able to stop in here at some point and look at that, and we'll do that in a little bit.
What we need, though, is we need to bind this form.
We're saying this input for customer name.
When I hit submit, we need to catch it on the server side.
I call it surviving the journey.
Okay. Yeah, it's a good point.
It does need to survive the journey.
So I'm gonna get rid of this OnGet here.
So we're gonna do a post.
You can say OnPost.
You could do it like this but the right way to do it is like this.
-Async? -Async, which means don't block, and we're gonna have a task that returns some action.
We might be doing something after this and I'm gonna say on OnPostAsync.
And it's giving me a little complaint here saying!
You didn't do a wait and you haven't returned a value.
Code paths, not all code paths return a value.
That's cuz we haven't done anything yet.
So, when someone posts back, they hit submit,and it posts back to here.
We would really like customer to have stuff in it.
-Yes -And so there's a couple things here.
And then we need to make sure that the state of that model is valid, that someone hasn't messed with it.
So I'm gonna say if ModelState.IsValid,or if it's not, pardon me- I was about to say something.
No I appreciate that.
Then return the page back to itself to say now I'm done.
If I hover over page you can see it returns a page result,which is a kind of action.
Returning a page is an action.
If we get this far, now I'm gonna say db,remember when I say db?
-Yes -What is db?
It is a applicationDB context.
In there is customers, plural.
-And we want to add one. -.Add().
We'll pass in the customer that we just got handed.
And then we'll say, hang out for a minute, await.
And we'll say, db.SaveChanges.
And async means don't wait.
Then we will go and return,not a page, because we're on the create page.
We really wanna return to the list.
Yeah, so you're doing a redirect?
We're gonna do a redirect, exactly.
And we haven't got a place to go yet.
But we'll say redirect to page.
Okay. And you can see that there's options like redirect to page permanent, which would be a 301.
Http 301.
Okay. We're gonna do a 302 because this is just a standard kind of redirect.
Let's just say /Index.
And I think we should probably just say /,but we'll see what happens.
If people wanted to learn more about 301s,302s, do you have any recommendations?
-The Internet. -Correct
I would search around for that kind of stuff.
Ultimately look at the docs.
Yeah. But redirect to page is a standard thing and again if you hover over it, it says right there Status302Found.
But if I said RedirectToPagePermanent.
We would change it?
Change it to a 301, which would tell the search engine,don't ever come back here and ask me about this again.
Don't ever talk to me again go here.
All right. That's what that means.
I'm paranoid so anyway,you never wanna do that when you're doing database work.
You always wanna be temporary, okay?
Okay. All right, and if you really,really, really wanna upset your coworkers.
You could move your curly braces.
Yeah.
And do stuff like this.
And if you really wanna be possibly buggy,you could even do stuff like this.
Where that's all one line.
Yeah?
But you might have other stuff that you wanna do.
Okay. Some people that really bothers them, some people it doesn't.
For me- Does it bother you?
I kinda like it on one line if it's not that big of a deal.
You know what I mean?
But as soon as you have an extra line then you're gonna go and undo it and take it apart.
It's stylistic.
So it's not really a best practice for someone to know of right now.
No, for right now, I just think it's nice to have everything fit on one line like that.
But using the curly mustaches.
Is curly braces,they look like a mustache if you turn your head.
That's a best practice.
It still gets us, that when people say curly braces, and I don't know what they're talking about
-What do you call them? -cuz I use brackets
You call them brackets?
So you have brackets, curly brackets, square brackets, so.
-Scandalous -Okay
-You're fancy -That is pretty intense.
-Yeah -Okay, now I'm going to put a break point here.
-Okay. And we'll see if this works -All right.
It might very well not work.
Fingers crossed and toes.
No, it's probably not gonna work.
Lower your expectations now.
-All right -Okay.
This is in create, right?
Yep. So I have to hit /create.
-Yeah -Okay
-Okay -Did we bind it?
-Yeah see what's happening? -Nothing.
No. And if we go and do a view source.
-And you go to? -Okay.
I just want to show the people the form first.
Some things showed up on the input that's kinda cool.
-That's kinda nice -That is
We didn't type that, right, remember?
So we're getting stuff on the input that we did not expect,which is cool.
I bet there's some request verification.
Yeah, they put a request verification token to keep people from tampering with our stuff.
There is your name=Customer.Name.
And it generated an id for us as well.
But you can see that nothing's happening.
On Customer, actually I wanna put a break point a little higher up, and then I'll explain to you what's going on.
-Okay -Let's see if we can even get to the post.
Okay, do a debug session again /create.
So I would've expected.
To hit that break point.
To hit that break point, so that's concerning.
But I know that I need to say BindProperty on the customer which is to tell it I want this customer object filled out with the form information, right?
-Yeah. -And right now I don't have that.
So let's take a look, and try this again.
The customer is gonna get created and filled up with information bound to those form fields.
If that doesn't work then I've forgotten something and we will go and have a little debugging which will be fun as well.
They say the definition of insanity is doing the same thing over and over and expecting a different result.
So let's take a look.
It's probably something obvious.
So we've got a form, we've got our input, we've got our method.
I said post, does it matter if it's all caps?
That would be odd if it did.
So it doesn't matter.
The tag helper exists already in view imports,the form is there.
The only thing l didn't add is the validation summary, okay?